你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到漏洞利用模块的另一个视频
welcome to yet another video in the exploitation scenarios module
我们将概况的讨论一下JIT spray
we're gonna talk about JIT spraying at a high level
当然，在这个模块（练习题中）你将尝试JIT spray
of course you will have to JIT spray in this module
这很令人激动
which will be super exciting
嗯
um
这里主要是对我们接触过的一个概念的回顾
this is mostly a review of a concept  that we touched on
我们在讨论DEP时讲过
when we talked about data execution prevention
但是让我们回顾一下安全机制
but let's recall security mitigations
在shellcode模块中，我们讨论了DEP
in the shellcode module we talked about data execution prevention
这可以防止执行注入的shellcode
which prevents the execution of injected shellcode
例如，让栈不可执行
by making for example the stack not executable
在内存错误模块
in the memory errors module
我们讨论了栈金丝雀，它可以防止栈缓冲区溢出被利用
we talked about stack canaries which protect against stack buffer overflow exploitation
还有ASLR，它使得控制流劫持变得不可靠
and address space layout randomization which makes control flow hijacking unreliable
这些保护机制让现代漏洞利用开发变的困难
so modern exploitation is hard because of all of this stuff
但让我们看看一种可以绕过DEP的方法
but let's look at a way  that we can bypass data execution prevention
主要针对采用了JIT编译的脚本程序
when just in time compilation is in play all right
什么是JIT编译
what is Just in time compilation well
JIT编译是一种非常聪明的技术
just in time compilation is a very clever technique
这使得我们每天依赖的解释型语言变得更快
that allows the interpret languages that we rely on every day to be fast
具体来说，最大的受益者 javascript
specifically the biggest biggest benefactor of this is javascript
还有一般的现代高级语言
modern higher level languages in general though
包括java, lua, python如果使用了pypy
including java, lua, python if you use the pypy python runtime
都采用了JIT编译技术
utilize just in time compilation
你可以选择javascript Java等语言来编写代码
you write the code in the language of choice javascript java etc
在运行时，如果某段代码被认为对性能至关重要
at runtime if code is deemed to be performance critical
它将被编译为二进制代码，而不是被解释
instead of being interpreted it will be compiled to binary code
这段二进制代码在执行的时候会非常快
and that binary code will then be extremely fast when it executes
当然了，所以
of course right so
根据你目前的经验
in your experience thus far
在逆向模块里你见到了Yan85(出现在练习题中的Yan教授自制虚拟机)
in the reversing module you saw Yan85
Yan85是一个解释型虚拟机
Yan85 is an interpreted virtual machine
在这里，你可以把它当作一个JIT编译器
here you'll see it as a just in time compiler
然后这样利用它
and you will have to exploit it that way
当然
now of course
生成的二进制代码
the code the binary code that's generated
与攻击者编写的高级语言代码有关
is related to the higher level language code that the attacker writes
或者说用户写的
or the user write
又或者一个网页提供的一些javascript
or a webpage provides some javascript
这些javascript会被编译成本地代码
that javascript gets compiled into native code
然后在受害者的机器上运行
and then runs on the machine of the victim
如果网站是恶意的，坏事就会发生
if the website is malicious bad things can happen
特别是一种叫做jit spray的攻击
specifically an attack called jit spraying
利用了JIT编译的特性
utilizes this interesting property of just in time compilation
它使攻击者可以控制内存的可执行区域中的值
that gives an attacker control of values in executable areas of memory
所以考虑下面这段javascript代码
so considered a following javascript
假设声明一个asdf变量初始化一个巨复杂的值
let's say you have var asdf equals and then a big complex crazy number
同样的也可以是
you can also imagine the same thing
Yan85中的IMM指令
the Yan85 statement of IMM or instruction of IMM
它将一个立即数赋给寄存器
that assigns an immediate to a register
它也可以有一个巨复杂的参数
could also have a crazy argument
如果Yan85虚拟机支持更高的位数
if Yan85 had more bits to play with
这段js代码可能会JIT编译成以下指令
this might JIT to the following native code
mov rdx, 值
move RDX the number
对，当然它会被汇编成指令对应的编码
right which assembles of course to some encoding of that instruction
这里是小端序表示的值
here is that number verbatim in little Endian
这个48，表示这是64位指令
and here is that 48  that says hey this is a 64 bit instruction
ba表示将立即数赋值给rdx
ba means move an immediate into RDX
单字节操作码，然后这是操作数
single byte opcode  and then here's the operand
如果有一个漏洞
alright but what if there was another vulnerability
能扰乱指令指针的计算方式，让它把值当作指令执行
that messed with the instruction pointer with how it was calculated to jump in
这个漏洞可能是
and then of course this other vulnerability might be
内存损坏，溢出覆盖指令指针的一个字节
a memory corruption overflowing one byte of the instruction pointer
有很多不同的可能性
a lot of potential different ways that can happen
如果我们不直接跳到指令的开头
but what if we jump not to the beginning of the instruction
而是跳转到指令开头的2字节后
but we jump 2 byte in
如果跳转到指令开头的2字节后，将从这里开始执行
if we jump 2 byte in we start executing right here
就好像这里开始才是指令
as if this was the beginning of the instruction
如果我们反汇编这个值
if we disassemble this code
它是被精心设计的exit系统调用的指令
it was carefully crafted to disassemble to an exit system call
当然也可以被设计成任何其他的系统调用
but of course it could be any other system call
只要我们在上层语言中精心设计常量值
so by carefully creating constants in our higher level language
这个上层语言可以是我们的模拟解释语言
in our emulate interpreted language
或者任何使用JIT的语言
or just in time compiled language rather
我们可以ummm
we can um cause um system calls to be umm
我们可以执行想要的代码
we can execute controlled native code
这很酷，但是
so that's cool but
alsr怎么绕过?
what about alsr
DEP只是
data execution prevention is only
我们目前讨论过的三种安全机制中的一种
one of the kind of trifecta of mitigations  that we talked about so far
在内存错误模块，讲了金丝雀的绕过或泄漏方法
we've seen ways to bypass stack canaries situational ways or leak them out  in the memory corruption module
但是地址空间布局随机化呢
but what about address space layout randomization
这个例子中只有一个变量
well this example just has one variable right here
但如果是这样呢？
what if you did something like this
我才发现很难看清
hard to see now I realize
这里声明了成百上千个相同的变量
but this is hundreds and hundreds of declarations of the same variable
这是一种偷懒的方法
and this is kind of a lazy way of doing it
还有更聪明的方法可以动态生成此代码
there are more intelligent ways you could dynamically generate this code
尤其是像javascript这样的高级语言
especially in javascript on high level languages like this
然后这些代码会被运行时编译成
and then that code would be just in time compiled into
包含你需要的常量的多个内存页
pages upon pages upon pages on pages that contain the Constants that you need
大大提高开启aslr后跳转命中率
and then you jump and hope you get lucky
前面的模块中体验过了暴力破解内存偏移量的方法
you've experienced brute forcing memory offsets already in the previous module
靶子越大，就越容易击中
the more code that you can jump to the easier that gets
这不是ASLR的完美解决方案
it's not a full solution to ASLR
但它能显著提高成功几率
but it helps improve success significantly
在非ASLR的其他随机性的背景下也是一样
in also in the context of other randomness from other sources other than ASLR
这就是JIT spray. 一项强大的技术
so that is jit spraying it's a powerful technique
到今天在很多情况下仍然是一个可用的攻击方法
and remains a usable attack vector in a lot of situations to this day
尤其是现在JIT的使用激增
especially as jits proliferate
有javascript java python lua等的JIT编译器
there are just in time compilers like I said for javascrip java python lua
它们都是不同的
and they're all different
它们都基于不同的代码，但有很多相同的bug
they're all based on different code bases of course with a lot of the same bugs
在这个模块中（练习题中）
um in this module
就像我暗示的那样
like I hinted
将遇到到Yan85的JIT编译器
you will see a just in time compiler for Yan85
祝你好运
good luck